Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Class Photographs collection, 1877-1992 MVC0023.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College class photographs collection
1877-1992
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon College
Mount Vernon Seminary
MVC0023.RG
13.5 Linear Feet 1 document box, 1 oversized flat box, 7 panorama photos in map folders, and 11 wrapped panorama photo plaques
This collection contains class photographs from Mount Vernon Seminary and College. The material dates from 1877 to 1992.
Arrangement
Organized into 1 series: Class photographs
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains Mount Vernon Seminary and College class photographs dating from 1877 to 1992.
Biographical / Historical
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875; she named it after her brother's church in Baltimore, Mount Vernon Place Methodist. The Seminary began as a six year prepatory school, with four years of high school level classes, and two years of post-high school curriculum, calling it a "Family and Day School for Young Ladies." In order to graduate, students had to complete a formal process of "Senior Essays" in which they completed primary research and wrote on a current political or social topic, including such provocative issues as child labor, prohibition, poverty, and women's suffrage. In the 1920 graduating class, eight women continued their education at universities such as the University of Wisconsin, Stanford, Northwestern and the University of Texas; by 1923 graduates were going to such other prestigious universities as UC-Berkeley, Columbia, Cornell, Smith College and the University of Chicago. Such advancements in higher education were uncommon for women of the day, but Mount Vernon was one of the premier prepatory institutions in the country.
In 1927, Mount Vernon established a Junior College, and with its establishment, students no longer had to complete six years of courses to receive a diploma; they graduated from the Seminary after four years and could continue on to the Junior College for two more years of college preparation. After World War II began, the U.S. Navy took over the campus as a part of the war effort; in 1945 the school purchased 21 acres on Foxhall Road and surrounding areas, and had applied for accreditation to award Associates of Arts Degrees after completing two years of the Junior College.
Despite its expansion, by 1965 the Board of Trustees voted unanimously to dissolve the Seminary by 1969, as it could not financially support both institutions. During the 1960s, the Junior College developed new academic concentrations such as government, international relations and political science to reflect its location in the nation's capital. At the same time, it began to phase out its vocational training such as home economics and secretarial skills to make room for these higher education courses.
By 1973, the Board of Higher Education licensed the college to award Bachelor of Arts (BA) degrees such as Public Affairs, Government, Business Administration, Childhood, Special Education, and the Visual Arts, as well as honorary Doctor of Humane Letters and Juris Doctor Degrees; in 1976, the college received initial accreditation as a four-year college and was reaccredited ten years later. However, by 1996 the college announced a plan to affiliate with George Washington University; in 1999 the last class of Mount Vernon College graduated. Today, as an affiliated campus of GWU, Mount Vernon offers special living accommodations, as well as learning and leadership programs for female students.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection came to Special Collections from the Mount Vernon campus in 2009.
Women's colleges
- Class photographs, 1877-1992; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically. Oversized items are housed separately.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Mount Vernon Seminary and College class photographs dating from 1877 to 1992.
  - Class photo, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Class photo, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Class photo, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1877, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1879, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1880, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1882, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1884, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1885, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1886, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Class of 1887, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Class of 1888, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Class of 1889, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Class of 1891, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Class of 1899, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Class of 1900, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Class of 1901, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Class of 1904, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Class of 1905, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1906, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Class of 1907, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Class of 1907, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1909, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Class of 1910, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Class of 1912, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Juniors 1914, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Class of 1919, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Class of 1920, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Junior Class of 1921, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Class of 1922 and Junior Class of 1922, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Class of 1923, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Class of 1924, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Class of 1929, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Class of 1944, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Class of 1945, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1949 Prep Graduates, 1949 College Graduates, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Class of 1955, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1956, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mr. Lloyd with 1957 Graduates, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Class of 1957, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Class of 1957, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Class of 1958, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Class of 1958, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Class of 1959, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Class of 1959, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Class of 1960, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Class of 1961, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Class of 1962, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Class of 1963, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Class of 1963, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Class of 1963, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Class of 1963, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Class of 1964 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Class of 1964, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Class of 1965, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Class of 1966, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Class of 1967, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Class of 1967, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Class of 1967, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Class of 1968, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Class of 1969, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Class of 1969, 1969 June 9; Series 1; Commencement photograph printed on wooden plaque. Includes corresponding names of graduating students. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1970, 1970 June 8; Series 1; Commencement photograph printed on wooden plaque. Includes corresponding names of graduating students. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1970 (2 copies), 1970 June 8; Series 1 (Map-case 23, Map-folder 1)
  - Class of 1971, 1971 June 6; Series 1 (Map-case 23, Map-folder 2)
  - Class of 1971, 1971 June 6; Series 1; Commencement photograph printed on wooden plaque. Includes corresponding names of graduating students. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1972 (2 copies), 1972 May 28; Series 1 (Map-case 23, Map-folder 3)
  - Class of 1973, Series 1 (Map-case 23, Map-folder 4)
  - Class of 1974, Series 1; Commencement photograph printed on wooden plaque. Includes corresponding names of graduating students. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1975, 1975 June 1; Series 1; Commencement photograph printed on wooden plaque. Includes corresponding names of graduating students. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1976, 1976 June 6; Series 1; Commencement photograph printed on wooden plaque. Includes corresponding names of graduating students. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1977, 1977 May 29; Series 1; Commencement photograph printed on wooden plaque. Includes corresponding names of graduating students. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1978, 1978 May 28; Series 1; Commencement photograph printed on wooden plaque. Includes corresponding names of graduating students. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1978 (2 copies), Series 1 (Map-case 23, Map-folder 5)
  - Class of 1979, Series 1 (Map-case 23, Map-folder 6)
  - Class of 1979, 1979 June 3; Series 1; Commencement photograph printed on wooden plaque. Includes corresponding names of graduating students. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1980, 1980 June 1; Series 1; Commencement photograph printed on wooden plaque. Includes corresponding names of graduating students. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1981, Series 1 (Map-case 23, Map-folder 7)
  - Class of 1981, 1981 May 31; Series 1; Commencement photograph printed on wooden plaque. Includes corresponding names of graduating students. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1992, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 28)